A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
The Library of Virginia
44696
32.32 cu. ft. (43 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of Natural Resources.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years (Code of Virginia 42.1-78). Types of records and information restricted include: Material protected by attorney-client privilege (2.2-3705.1) and personal information (2.2-3801). It will be necessary for an archivist to review and remove or redact confidential records or information before the records can be used by patrons for research purposes or before any copies can be made. If you are planning to use these records, please contact Archives Reference Services for more details prior to planning your research trip.
Acquisition Information
Accession 44696 transferred by Carol B. Denson, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Va., 14 January 2010.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governor's top management team. The Office of Secretary of Commerce and Resources was created on April 8, 1972. The Secretary of Commerce and Resources was responsible for assisting the Governor in implementing policies for the conservation and use of natural resources, for promoting economic development, providing managerial guidance and direction to Commerce and Resources agencies, and developing and promoting Commerce and Resources programs and budgets. In 1984 the Secretariat was split into two separate offices, the Secretary of Economic Development and the Secretary of Natural Resources.
The Secretary of Natural Resources is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, and is subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary of Natural Resources was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over, the following state agencies and boards: Department of Conservation and Recreation, Department of Environmental Quality, Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, Department of Historic Resources, Marine Resources Commission, Museum of Natural History, and the Virginia Council on Indians. The Secretary of Natural Resources also served as the chairman of the Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, and was a Board Member of the Chesapeake Bay Commission. Additionally, the Secretary of Natural Resources was responsible for many smaller boards and commissions related to water control, pollution, rivers, waste management, and other environmental and recreational issues.
L. Preston Bryant, Jr., was appointed Secretary of Natural Resources in January 2006 and served for the entire administration of Governor Tim Kaine. Prior to serving as Secretary of Natural Resources, Bryant served as a member of the House of Delegates for ten years, representing the greater Lynchburg area. After the end of the administration, Bryant became a senior vice president at McGuireWoods Consulting in Richmond, Va.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the records, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), of the Office of Secretary of Natural Resources L. Preston Bryant, Jr., during the administration of Governor Tim Kaine. There is correspondence and subject files that relate to Secretary Bryant, the state agencies that he oversees, environmental organizations that operate in Virginia, and projects initiated by Governor Kaine. Legislative files contain material related to bills that were either under the purview of the Secretary of Natural Resources or upon which the Secretary wished to comment. Special programs include correspondence and subject files primarily created by Assistant Secretary of Natural Resources Missy Neff and Deputy Secretary of Natural Resources Nikki Rovner. Finally, there are speeches given by L. Preston Bryant, Jr., at public and private events.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence and subject files
II. Legislative files
III. Special programs
IV. Speeches
Wherever possible, the original order of the files has been maintained.
Related Material
OFFICE OF THE GOVERNOR-TIM KAINE
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). The Secretary of Natural Resources Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine administration. This series contains 48529 emails in eight (8) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. L. Preston Bryant, Jr. Email; B. Nikki Rovner Email; C. Jeff Corbin Email; D. Missy Neff Email; E. Carol Denson Email; F. Bill Norris Email; G. Paula Jasinski Email; and H. Kathleen Onufer Email. There are 177 protected and confidential emails that are restricted from public access per Code of Virginia, 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, personnel information, Workmen's Compensation claims, confidentiality agreements, and settlement discussions. The Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal provides access to the Kaine email collection and includes guides to other Kaine administration records.
The Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Anne Holton), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Bob McDonnell and William C. Mims), two statewide officials elected in the same cycle as Governor Kaine.
The Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports Digital Collection contains the weekly reports submitted to the Governor and Chief of Staff by the Governor's Cabinet, including the Secretaries of Administration (Viola Baskerville), Agriculture and Forestry (Robert S. Bloxom), Commerce and Trade (Patrick O. Gottschalk), Commonwealth (Daniel C. LeBlanc, Jan-Mar. 2006 and Katherine K. Hanley (Mar. 2006-2010), Education (Dr. Thomas R. Morris), Finance (Jody Wagner, 2006-2008 and Richard D. Brown, 2008-2010), Health and Human Resources (Marilyn Tavenner), Natural Resources (Preston Bryant), Public Safety (John W. Marshall), Technology (Aneesh Chopra, 2006-2009 and Leonard M. Pomata, 2009-2010), and Transportation (Pierce Homer). Also included are reports by the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness (Robert Crouch), Office of Constituent Services (Marc Cheatham, 2006-2007 and Amber Amato, 2007-2010), Press Office, Policy Office and Virginia Liaison Office. Reports were submitted each Thursday and placed in a binder for the Governor that he took with him at the end of the day on Friday. A second copy of the report was made for the Chief of Staff. The level of detail varied for each cabinet officer and items of importance were highlighted by staff for the Governor. Each report contains information on legislation, Governor's initiatives/special projects, agency matters/operations, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues and pending decisions. Governor Kaine wrote handwritten notes and/or marked-up some reports with post-it notes and requested follow up information from the person submitting the report. Those questions and answers are included in this series. This series provides a weekly account of the issues and policy decisions of the Kaine Administration.
The Executive Orders Digital Collection includes 110 executive orders and 9 executive directives issued by Governor Kaine.
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). The Policy Office Records of Governor Timothy M. Kaine are housed in 174 boxes. The collection is arranged into five (5) series. Series have been designated for: I. Decision Briefs; II. Regulations; III. Legislative Files; IV. Executive Orders and Directives; and V. Policy Analyst Files. These records include agendas, decision briefs, correspondence, memorandums, legislative files, briefing books, meeting notes, subject files, reports, talking points and regulations. These records document the legislative and policy priorities of the Kaine administration (2006-2010). This collection also includes records from Governor Mark Warner's administration (2002-2006).
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Liaison Office, 2003-2010 (bulk 2006-2009. The Virginia Liaison Office records, 2003-2009 (bulk 2006-2009), are housed in 34 boxes. The collection includes series for Director's correspondence and subject files, Policy Analyst correspondence and subject files, National Governor's Association, and Southern Governor's Association.
LIVE WEBSITES
The Virginia General Assembly's Legislative Information System contains searchable databases for bills and resolutions from 1994 to the present and reports to the general assembly. It also includes links to the Code of Virginia, Virginia Administrative Code, Constitution of Virginia, Charters, Authorities, Compacts and Uncodified Acts.
Contents List
- I. Correspondence and subject files, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2010)., 27.22 cu. ft. (30 boxes)
  This series contains the correspondence and subject files, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2010), of the Office of the Secretary of Natural Resources. There is constituent correspondence on a wide range of topics, which includes the cap on menhaden fishing, the death of the bears at Maymont in Richmond, and the Governor's 400,000-acre conservation goal, among many others. There is also the correspondence and subject files of Secretary of Natural Resources L. Preston Bryant, Jr, which includes his correspondence with members of Congress, members of Tim Kaine's administration, and the general public. There is also correspondence and subject files relating to the state agencies that are overseen by the Secretary of Natural Resources: the Department of Conservation and Recreation, the Department of Environmental Quality, the Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, the Department of Historic Resources, the Virginia Museum of Natural History, the Virginia Marine Resources Commission, and the Virginia Council on Indians. Finally, there is correspondence relating to various environmental organizations that operate in Virginia as well as material relating to projects initiated by Governor Tim Kaine.
  Wherever possible, the original order of folders has been maintained.
  - Constituent correspondence, 2006-2009.
    Contains correspondence from Virginians about a wide range of topics. There are a significant amount of letters relating to the cap on menhaden fishing, the death of the bears at Maymont in Richmond, and the Governor's 400,000-acre conservation goal, among many others. There are also proclamations issued by the Secretary of Natural Resources, as well as decision briefs and Freedom of Information Act requests.
    Arranged by the ID number given to each constituent request.
    - Incoming ID numbers 2574506-2604063, 2006. (Box 1)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2604064-2618979, 2006. (Box 2)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2619041-2634073 and Menhaden Cap letters, 2006. (Box 3)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2630425-2677236, 2007. (Box 4)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2677273-2699898, 2007. (Box 5)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2700108-2738003, 2007-2008. (Box 6)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2738018-2764988, 2008. (Box 7)
    - Incoming ID numbers 2765024-2868790, 2008-2009. (Box 8)
    - Virginia Freedom of Information Act requests 2006-2009. (Box 9)
    - Proclamations, recognition requests, etc. 2006-2009. (Box 9)
    - Secretary of Natural Resources decision briefs, 2006-2009. (Box 9)
  - Secretary's correspondence and subject files, 2003-2010., 6.12 cu. ft. (7 boxes)
    Contains the correspondence and subject files of Secretary of Natural Resources L. Preston Bryant, Jr. Includes the Secretary's chronological reading file, which contains the outgoing correspondence of L. Preston Bryant, Jr. There is also correspondence both to and from members of Congress about topics relating to projects of the Secretary of Natural Resources. General correspondence includes emails and letters from constituents and Secretary Bryant's response to them. Finally, there are subject files which contain correspondence, minutes, meeting material, and notes, among other items, related to various boards upon which the Secretary of Natural Resources served.
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 January-July. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Chronological reading file, 2006 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 January-June. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 January-June. (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 January-June. (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 January-June. (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 January-June. (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 January-June. (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 July-December. (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 July-December. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 July-December. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 July-December. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 July-December. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Chronological reading file, 2007 July-December. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Chronological reading file, 2008. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Chronological reading file, 2009. (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Chronological reading file, 2009. (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Chronological reading file, 2009. (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Chronological reading file, 2009. (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Chronological reading file, 2009. (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Chronological reading file, 2010. (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - U.S. Congress, 2007-2009. (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - U.S. Congress, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - U.S. Congress, 2006-2007. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 January-June. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 January-June. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 January-June. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 July-December. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 July-December. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 July-December. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 July-December. (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, 2006 July-December. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 January-July. (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 January-July. (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 January-July. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 January-July. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 January-July. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 January-July. (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 2007 August-December. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - General Correspondence, 2008 July-December. (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 January-June. (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 January-June. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 January-June. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 January-June. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 July-December. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 July-December. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, 2009 July-December. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, 2010. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Shenandoah River Endangered Listing, 2006. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Smith Mountain Lake FERC Re-Licensing, 2007-2008. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Statewide Agencies Radio System, 2006. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Surplus Real Property, 2006-2007. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Thoroughbred Retirement Program with the Department of Corrections, 2006-2007. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Transition, 2005. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Army Corps of Engineers: City of Franklin Flood Study, 2006-2007. (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - United States Army Corps of Engineers, 2006-2007. (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - United States Army Corps of Engineers: Lynnhaven River, 2007. (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - United States Army Corps of Engineers Project Cooperation, 2006. (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Attorney General's Office: Pleadings Received, 2006-2010. (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Big Sandy Coalition, 2007. (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Blandy Experimental Farm, 2007-2008. (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Claytor Nature Study Center Task Force, 2007-2008. (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Dodona, 2007. (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Dominion Transmission Line: Valley/NOVA, 2006-2009. (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Economic Development, 2006. (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Eighth and Ninth Street Office Buildings, 2004-2005. (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Governor's Environmental Excellence Awards Program Revisions, 2007. (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - National Forest Roadless Areas, 2006. (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - National Forest Roadless Areas, 2005-2006. (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Offshore drilling, 2006-2007. (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Federal Outlying Landing Field, 2003. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Federal Outlying Landing Field, 2007. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Federal Outlying Landing Field, 2007-2008. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Uranium Mining, 2007-2009. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Executive Institute, 2006. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Horse Center, 2006. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Wolseley/Ferguson Newport News Expansion, 2005-2006. (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - The American Civil War Center, 2006. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Civil Rights Memorial Commission, 2006. (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Ft. Monroe Federal Area Development Authority Board Minutes, 2007. (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Ft. Monroe Federal Area Development Authority Board Minutes, 2008. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Ft. Monroe Federal Area Development Authority Board Minutes, 2009. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Ft. Monroe Reuse Steering Committee, 2006. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Jamestown 2007 Steering Committee, 2006. (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous Appointments, 2006-2009. (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Board Meeting, 2009. (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Board Meeting, 2007. (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation, 2007-2009. (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Grant Criteria Revision, 2007. (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Meeting Materials, 2007-2009. (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Meeting Materials, 2006-2007. (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Meeting Minutes, 2006. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Sesquicentennial of the American Civil War Commission, 2007. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Assigned state agencies, 1999-2010., 10.35 cu. ft. (11 boxes)
    Contains correspondence and subject files relating to the state agencies that are overseen by the Secretary of Natural Resources: the Department of Conservation and Recreation, the Department of Environmental Quality, the Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, the Department of Historic Resources, the Virginia Museum of Natural History, the Virginia Marine Resources Commission, and the Virginia Council on Indians. Mission statements for each of the agencies under the Secretary's purview were taken from the website of the Secretary of Natural Resources as found in the Governor Timothy Kaine Administration Collection, 2006-2010 and as captured on 15 January 2010.
    - General, 2006-2010.
      This subseries contains information that relates to all of the assigned state agencies that fall under the purview of the Secretary of Natural Resources. It includes material about agency head meetings, the Small Business, Women, and Minorities purchasing plans, and reviews of each agency's strategic plan.
      - Agency head meetings, 2006-2009. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Agency SWaM Plans, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Agency SWaM Plans, 2008. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Agency SWaM Plans, 2009. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Agency SWaM Plans, 2010. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Printing Requests, 2009. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Post Katrina and Rita Evaluations, 2006. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Assessment of Mandates by Executive Agencies, 2008. (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Review of Agencies' Strategic Plans, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Review of Agencies' Strategic Plans, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Review of Agencies' Strategic Plans, 2009. (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Review of Agencies' Strategic Plans, 2009. (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Department of Conservation and Recreation, 2004-2009.